So I want to thank you, for taking the
algorithmic think thinking course with us,
you know Joe, Scott and I are all very
happy to have had you in the course, and
we hope that you learned interesting stuff
from the course, we truly believe in
the significance and the importance of
the material we delivered in this course.
As we had mentioned, we had offered
this course at Rice University for
four years now, and
it has been very successful.
We offered you a version
of that course here and
we hope that you also got
the same type of material and
the same type of experience,
that we also offered to Rice students.
And I want to summarize
briefly what we have,
what is this process of algorithmic
thinking, that we have been following.
And what is it that we have
done throughout this course.
And as a reminder, you know, I defined
algorithmic thinking from the beginning of
the course, as a five step process.
And that five step process, is really
motivated by the way I look at research
and the, the, my research involving,
domains outside computer science.
In particular biology.
So the first step in the problems
when I'm dealing with a biologist or
when I'm working on
a problem from biology.
Is to understand the problem.
What is it that,
what is that the biologists wants from me?
What is that input,
that they're going to provide me.
Are they going to give me DNA sequences?
Are they going to give
me homgeno sequences?
Are they going to give me some
information about gene expression?
Are they going to give me
a interaction network?
So what is it that they are going to give
me, and what is it that they want from me?
One, the first,
when I understand all these details,
what is it that they want to give,
what is it that they want to, to get back?
Now I formulate the problem, and this
is where math, comes into the picture.
The formulation, the problem formulation,
which is the second step in
algorithmic thinking, is really
mathematics, more than algorithms.
Here we have to use our skills,
in mathematics to represent
the problem cleanly.
For example, if the biologist has
given me DNA sequences, I have to say,
that these sequences can be best
represented as strings, right, which
are basically mathematical structures,
that we have talked about, okay?
We will present these as strings.
I have to define some sort of
a mathematical criterion that says,
what are the, the constraints on these
strings to make them DNA strings,
what are the constraints on the output,
in terms of what the biologist wants,
as a feasible solution, and
what is an optimal criterion.
If a biologist wants a good, solution,
what makes a solution good, right?
We have to define that mathematically,
so that an algorithm can run,
on the on a space of possible candidates
and find the good solution okay?
So first step understand the problem.
Second is formulated mathematically
in terms of input and output.
The third thing,
we come up with an algorithm, okay?
Once we come up with algorithm,
we have seen some algorithmic
strategies in the course.
Including divide and conquer.
Including dynamic programming,
we have seen graph exploration and so on.
Of course there's brute force, but
we have seen that brute force is not,
the most interesting or
the most feasible thing in most scenarios.
So the third step, we are interested
in coming up with an algorithm.
We can,
the first thing that we think about,
is, okay what algorithmic
strategies are out there.
Are, is the problem we are dealing win,
I mean,
with amenable to some of these strategies,
or
do we need to come up with a new algorithm
or a new strategy to solve the problem.
And this usually one of the most
challenging steps in algorithmic thinking,
because coming up with an algorithm for
a problem from scratch,
is not a trivial task.
Okay?
So, we have see,
some of algorithmic techniques.
But beyond this course,
there are many more advanced courses.
Whether they're like traditionally
combinatorial, algorithms, or
more modern algorithms that deal with
statistical inference problems, and so.
There are lots of courses out there,
that we highly recommend that you take and
explore algorithms, beyond what you
have seen in algorithmic thinking.
Once we come up with an algorithm.
We make sure it is correct, we analyze its
correctness, we analyze its efficiency.
We have talked about, running time and
asymptotics to make sure that we can,
reason about how efficient
an algorithm is before we even move to
the implementation fees, because as
we have discussed in this course,
if the running time of an algorithm grows.
A symptotic like two to the N,
where N is the input size, and
you know that the size of the input is
going to be on the order of thousands or
tens of thousands, you know that that
algorithm is not going to be worth,
implementing because it's going to,
be unfeasible in practice.
So, once we have come up with
an algorithm, reasoned about it's
efficiency and correctness, the fourth
step is implementing the algorithm.
You have done implementation
throughout the, the course with us.
Where every algorithm was implemented
in a, in a programming language.
You had to test it and
you have to, to go back and
forth between the pseudo code,
and the actual implementation.
As I said from the beginning.
One of the interesting things of
going from the pseudocode, to the,
to the actual code, to the actual
implementation, is that that step,
presents us with opportunities, but
also presents some dangers there.
The opportunities, in, in the,
in the form that you can actually use your
implementation or coding skills to take
pseudocode and make, actually,
a more efficient implementation of it.
Because when we present through
the code it's basically we
are describing what the algorithm does.
Not how it does every step in detail.
When we want to present how things
are done in detail that's when we
go to the actual implementation.
And you have seen I hope,
throughout the course,
is that when we present pseudo
code in the homework or wherever.
And you are writing the implementation
of that pseudo code.
In many, many situations, you even made
the, the pseudo code more, more efficient.
Okay?
But the second thing also as I said,
there is the danger of
going from a correct pseudo code,
to an incorrect implementation.
And again, you have noticed that
in this course that sometimes when
you implemented the, the piece of code.
Even though the pseudo code is correct,
you notice that you had to go through many
iterations, of that implementation
phase until you got it right, okay?
So, the first, the fourth step is, is that
implementation of the pseudo code, but
it's not a trivial step
by any means right?
Because, you have to make
the implementation efficient.
You have to make sure it is correct.
And there are, there is a lot of room for
efficiency, and there's a lot of room for
in-correctness, as well
that you have to avoid.
After we are done with that, the fifth
step in our algorithmic thinking is to
take that code, run it on the data and
reason about it.
And I would say, this is really
what distinguishes our course,
from a traditional algorithms course,
where we had that application part.
Where we try to emphasize
this notion that,
an algorithm is not just a mathematical
object that we implement, for fun.
Some people do have fun, with coming up
with algorithms or implementing them.
But usually they are part of a larger
application that we are trying to solve or
to develop.
And the application component in,
in the algorithmic thinking.
Was designed, to illustrate this notion.
So, we wanted you to
take that implementation,
apply it to actual data set,
get an output, and reason about it.
And every now and then even make
connection to the symptotic analysis and
so on that you have done
in the theoretical part.
Okay?
So, again, this is the five step
process of algorithmic thinking.
Where, we basically understand
the problem, formulate the problem,
come up with an algorithm, implement
the algorithm, and then analyze the,
the original data that we were presented
with, so that we give solutions.
Okay.
Algorithmic thinking is a very powerful
technique, especially these days when,
when computer science is spreading,
in terms of applications way beyond
traditional computer science.
So now we,
the community talks about X plus CS, or
X plus computer science
where X can be any domain.
Biology plus computer science,
physics plus computer science,
social sciences plus computer science.
So, algorithmic thinking,
is actually everywhere in this fields.
Okay?
And we highly recommend that, this is
just the beginning, that you start if you
enjoy it or you like algorithmic thinking,
that you start, honing more skills, that
will allow you to practice this kind of
pro process in practice, which basically
means, you need to take more mathematic
courses, more algorithm courses and so on.